This is the sun
This is the moon
すすきの山の ここは地球
And this is my grandmother
My, aren't they beautiful!
Well, if it isn't Mrs. Yamada
I've never seen such magnificent flowers...
Yep, they're like my children
And what do you call this one?
Ah, this one is Mino Chrysanthemum...
and this one is the large flowering...
Not the flowers, this bug
Beats me
Turn into a butterfly as beautiful as this flower, you hear?
Mother!
That's my grandmother
And this is my mother and me, Nonoko
What am I going to make for dinner tonight?
I've got it!
What are you making?
All last week we had curry, but
tonight let's do curry!
And this is my father and older brother
Dad, what's the point of studying this?
Listen, Noboru
Studying isn't about what's useful or not
What may seem useless now
may turn out to be useful
What I mean is,
useful studying may turn out to be useless
and useless studying may turn out to be useful
When it comes in handy
it's not about whether it's useful or useless
Seriously, what are you going on about?
I guess it's important after all
Wow,
If my father was smart and cool
and my mother was beautiful, stylish, and a good cook
and we had more money
my life would have been totally different
If one of them had...
Don't be stupid
If we hadn't gotten married, you wouldn't have been born
If one of us was different, you wouldn't be here
Not necessarily,
If I'd had different parents I'd just be cooler
You're ridiculous
Don't you know about the birds and the bees?
??? you have to sow seeds ???
That's right
You can't choose your parents
I don't believe that
It just doesn't seem right
I'm me, dad's dad, and mom's mom, right?
What's that supposed to mean?
Who are you?
Where did I come from?
Where am I?
Who am I?
Whoa,
Mom and dad weren't always married
In celebration of their new life together
let's give a heartfelt round of applause to Takashi and Matsuko
Matsuko, Takashi
Congratulations
And to their parents and relatives
I offer my heartfelt congratulations
As for you two
I wish you smooth sailing on your journey
across the open seas
船出しやはったわけです set sail
Life has its ups and downs
時には 大波になぶられて Especially you will be tormented big waves
??? (奈落の底にIn the abyss (突き落とされたり…な pushed into（せやけどね) そうだけど
Don't worry
Carrying on by oneself and
seeing things through to the end is admirable, but
???
Together,
大概は 切り抜けられるもんです you can get through most anything
Isn't that right?
Here's some advice
Have children as soon as possible
You can overcome life's troubles
?? 子供.....と決まっとります
Nowadays raising kids can seem troublesome
and difficult, but
People have been doing it since long ago
It's said that even without parents, children grow up
Once they can crawl, they stand
Once they can stand, they walk
And when you hold them close,
they can get through most anything
さて、子を持って知る親の恩
they think that parents are just annoying, but
子供は預かって貰えるし they're taken care of,
and, more importantly, bought toys
子供を持って 初めて 親の.....恩を知った と When you first have kids
If you make a mistake
be sure to remember this old saying:
"Oh, I get it now"
それも親の恩のうちや
In other words, うまいこといくと
親の土地 建物
当てに できるかもわかりません you don't know if you can count on
Anyway, Matsuko,
Takashi,
From now on, 今から　親を大事にせな あきまへんで
For your information
this land's in my name
With all due respect,
I built this house
If there was no land, you couldn't build a house
And you know I always thank you for that,
but try to see all the hard work I've put in
Your room gets the best light...
Yeah, thanks a lot
That's to be expected...
since you built on my land
Besides, you
didn't build this house yourself
Look,
If we're talking about this house, make no mistake, I...
Cut it out, you two!
It's shameful!
That's right!
What's the point of all this fighting?
What he said!
Eventually it will be my house anyway
By the way,
On the path to a long life
What's the scariest thing?
A raging storm?
A raging stream?
Actually, in the calmest seas
Matsuko and Takashi,
Go right at that corner!
Right!
Left!
Right up here, no left!
Speak clearly!
Hmm, maybe it was a right.
Which is it?!
We almost had it
Our turn!
The breakdown of the family
Is this some kind of detour?
Turn at this light
No, straight! Go straight!
It's over there. What are you talking about?
Dad, we should have gone this way
Shut up!
???
The only one who's being quiet is Nonoko
Oh
She's not in the car
Nonoko?
Why's she not in the car?
Well anyway, stop the car!
Where'd we leave her?
Noboru,
Weren't you with Nonoko?
Yea, with Dad while we waited on you guys.
Maybe she got bored and wandered off
No way, she was sitting on the bench with us
Thanks for waiting
Took you long enough!
Sorry, I thought we'd be finished soon
I had places I wanted to go
We won't have enough time to go to the sports store!
That's it!
It must have been there!
It's your fault for rushing us
It's not my fault!
You never have to wait!
In all the excitement she got left behind
Poor thing...
What are you talking about? Like it's somebody else's problem
Weren't we looking at clothes for you?
The sports store is closed! We missed it!
You're just thinking about yourself
If it was you, how would you feel?
What do you mean?
Maybe...she was kidnapped?
かわいいやろ わたしに似て
This is no laughing matter!
In this situation, one thing could be of some help
What is it?
The PTA slogan:
"If a stranger talks to you, use caution!"
Are they teaching such stupid things to children?
Then you just think everyone is a thief
With those teeth, she'll be fine
Cake!
Gimme some!
Ok, just one bite
Ok
She'll bite them for sure!
Idiot
Will you let me in?
I think my daughter's been abducted
We need to call them
We should have called earlier...
That's why we should have cell phones
You be quiet!
Poor Nonoko!
Are you lost?
Umm...
Are you waiting on someone?
Who are you waiting for?
Can't you talk?
Why aren't you saying anything?
You're a stranger...
I can't talk to you
That's right. "Use caution when talking to strangers." That thing?
You're great!
用心したもん もうお話しても大丈夫だよ
Wow, you're really great
My father, mother, grandma and older brother are all lost
Did you get separated from someone?
Yeah,
my mom...
Your mom!
Mom's gone...
Wow, I guess lost parents are getting common
But it's just your mother, you'll find her soon!
Excuse me,
This is Kimura Toshio. Can you call his mother?
Lost, huh?
Not lost, just separated
Oh I see
Let's see. Mr. Kimura, what's your first name?
Toshio!
Toshio, right?
Ok, please wait here a moment
And who are you? The older sister?
Nope
My whole family got lost
♪ Little lost Koneko ♪
♪ Where did you come -- ♪
Don't cry. We're here
What do you mean she went with her mother?
I'm her mother!
Is that so?
あんた　ようもウチの子を
Maybe it wasn't her mother, but it seemed like someone she knew
Someone she knew?
Who could it be?
I have no idea
知り合いのようなフリして
No, she was called by her mother
It wasn't her mother!
Don't make a fuss!
And then?
They apologized
And then Nonoko left happily with the person who was like her mother
Who could it be?
Anyhow, can you call for Nonoko?
Well, the two of them walked out of that exit
She's not there.
Come on!
I wonder what happened?
Dad, where are we going in such a hurry?
We're in pursuit
Of what?
Isn't it obvious? The car Nonoko's in
What kind of car is it?
Oh, which way did they go?
It's OK
It was some lady that knew Nonoko, right?
She'll take her home
He's got a point
Yes, that's it!
Don't be so naive. The person she knows could be dangerous
Mom!
警察に届けたら ええやろな
The police!?
Why on Earth are you talking about this?
Just telling you the truth
The truth?
Four adults neglecting a young girl
The abandoned child was eaten
Does Nonoko have a key?
Let's go home!
Nonoko!
当たり前や 閉まっとったんやから
Hello? This is Mrs. Yamada
Oh thank goodness!
I can't thank you enough!
Oh no, no, we were looking all over
Sorry for all the trouble
Could you bring her over soon?
No, no, we'll come get her
And you even fed her dinner!
That's so kind of you
I don't know how to thank you...
At last I got through to them
Seems like they just got back
She'll be here soon to pick you up
Sorry, auntie
It's nothing!
I love to hear what's going on with the Yamada family
秋の夜を　打崩したる　咄かな -- Basho
Blue sky
white clouds
そのうち なんとか
なるだろう
Approaching Ichinin-mae
The bus will stop at the next stop
What stop was it?
For now don't push the button, please.
家政の天才
It started raining
I left the laundry out!
Huh?
What'd you say?
Oh yeah! I brought it in already
No, you forgot to hang it!
I'm stepping out for a bit
Need anything from the store?
Ah, there was something...
Oh what was it?
Well, I'm going
We needed...oh what was it?
W-w-wait a second!
What is it?
It was, uh, uh...
Get yourself together!
Ah! White bread!
As you wish!
Mom!
I'll pay you back!
I'm home!
Huh, mom's not home?
There's udon!
And there's water boiling!
I'll eat it before anyone notices
Oh, welcome home!
Were you hiding?
Huh?
The light is out
That's no good, we'll have to change it
Darnit
I thought we had a spare
For now, just switch it with one we rarely use
Borrowing this for a bit
Ouch!
Can I have some tea?
Me too!
I'm busy with the dishes!
One of you get it!
Rock, paper, scissors, shoot!
Get a cup for yourself
And can I get you to finish up the dishes?
What??
Mr. Tanaka is going to drop by
What am I gonna do?!
I guess we need to pick up a little
What are you doing?
I was cleaning up
There we go
我が家の夫婦道
It's on the kitchen table!
I don't see it
Look carefully, I know I left it there
It's not there
Where are you looking?
It's an envelope with "OKK" written on it in red
Sir, is it this?
No, no it's OK.
If it's not there, it's not there
主婦２０年　ダテじゃないね
Can I see the paper?
After I'm finished
大したもんで
Dear,
While you're out, can you pick up some things?
Sure thing
Lettuce, cucumber, ham, light bulbs, and trash bags
I'll write it down
It's OK, I'll remember
Lettuce, cucumber, ham...light bulbs, and trash bags, right?
Did I forget something?
Lettuce, cucumber...
Hurry up and decide
You've already decided?
ああ　早くしろってば
Oh! Maybe I'll do this Shanghai set lunch
Me too
Two Shanghai set lunches
What are you still doing here?
What do you mean?
Can't a husband take a break now and then?
It's just that you usually go to the pachinko parlor
今日は禁パチ日だ
Can I get some tea?
I think I'd like udon for lunch
Ok, Ok
Actually, I'd like coffee instead of tea
Oh yeah,
when I went just now the bathroom was dirty
Make sure to clean it
Another thing,
when you get groceries, can you pick me up some cigarettes?
It's one thing after another with him
Dear?
Where's mom?
She went to pachinko
Kuwata's only given up one run in five games
Kuwata throws the pitch
It's a hit!
It's up and to the right
Takahashi makes the catch
That's three outs
８回の裏
ジャイアンツは一番の西からの攻？？ということになるわけです
Tonight's broadcast is brought you by...
Perfect! It's just starting now
Kuwata's defense is great, isn't it?
Yes, truly great
It's not over yet
Oh but I was looking forward to watching it
No way!
I want to watch the movie!
You can't even watch TV
This is better than TV
I got it!
Hey Noboru
Wanna play catch?
Sure
Father-son talk
Don't Enter
Wait a sec
Usually the parent catches, right?
You're a loud one, aren't you?
Let's go
This is a curveball
This is a screwball
This is a fastball
Isn't he annoying
Ready? Two outs, bases loaded, you're the relief pitcher
No way, I'm a starting pitcher
Annoying, aren't they?
What are you talking about?
野球部じゃピッチャーなんか
That's why I should pitch the whole game
Alright, that makes sense
Let's try to pitch the whole game
But...two outs bases loaded
Let's go
Hey!
Dad, what are you listening to?
If you listen to this tape over and over your English will improve
Isn't that a little naive?
In my experience,
you need to study
study, study, study, study, study
study, study, study
study!
全然やる気にならないよ
一緒にすんな
Want to try a little sake?
Sure
Dear!
How is it? No good?
It's dry, isn't it?
What'd you say?
Well, I...
Why, you little!
Noboru!
Hey Noboru
Shall we play catch?
Why?
What do you mean 'why'?
For a little father-son talk, as they say
In that case we don't have to play catch, do we?
Well, that's true, but
The environment is also important
It's OK. It's too much trouble
Kids these days...
深刻な親子の断絶やな That kind of relationship is going extinct
父権の回復
Noboru! You don't put rice into miso soup!
You know better!
You put the miso soup into the rice.
I disagree
Why? What's the problem?
Do what you want, then
Look,
You put the water into the cement!
Don't hover with your chopsticks over the food. It's rude
When you've decided on something, take it with purpose
That's my plate
Sorry.
返しなさんな　食べさしを
Dad, I need to think of my free research topic
What do you mean?
If it's a free topic, can't you choose anything you like?
That's true, but I can't come up with anything
You can do anything, right?
Yeah, anything
Well,
If you told me "you can write about anything you want"
I'd draw a blank too
That's what I'm saying.
Anything, huh?
What should you do? Anything?
Sought after freedom
The freedom of your dreams
Freedom that's finally held out in front of you
but you don't know what to do
He turned into a philosopher
He's just thinking about retirement
親父の背中